All right. בוקר
טוב *Boker Tov* and welcome to מסכת זבחים *Masechet Zvachim*. We're on
דף *Daf* 20, כ *Kaf*, very last line of יט עמוד ב
*Yud Tet Amud Bet*. I just want to review with us the
פסוק pasuk *pasuk* which is the source of our discussion in this
morning.
We are in שמות *Shmot* 19, chapter 30, verse 19 and 20.
ורחצו אהרן ובניו ממנו את ידיהם ואת רגליהם *Verachatzu Aharon uvanav mimenu
et yedeihem ve'et ragleihem*, so Aaron and his children will wash their
hands and feet, בבואם bevo'am, אל אהל מועד *bevo'am el Ohel Moed*
when they come, ירחצו מים ולא ימותו *yirchatzu mayim velo yamutu*, they'll
wash their hands and not die, או בגשתם *o begishtam*, and we
had yesterday a lengthy discussion about בבואם be-vo'am *bevo'am* ובגשתם *u-begishtam*,
is it when they come in or is it when they approach
the service, אל המזבח לשרת *el hamizbe'ach lesharet*, okay, like of course,
they come to serve, להקטיר אשה לה' *lehaktir isheh laHashem*, so the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* where we begin this morning at the bottom of
יט עמוד ב *Yud Tet Amud Bet* is the question of why
do I need the end of this פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*? This פסוק
*pasuk* would have been fine just without it. We could have told
about the כהנים kohanim, *Kohanim* that they need to wash hands and
feet when they come or when they approach the אהל מועד *Ohel
Moed* and the מזבח mizbeach *mizbe'ach*, but what is the added value
of להקטיר אשה לה' *lehaktir isheh laHashem*? And so the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is asking, להקטיר אשה למה לי *lehaktir isheh lama li*? Top
of כ *Kaf*. מהו דתימא הני מילי עבודה avoda דמעכבת כפרה אבל
עבודה avoda דלא מעכבת כפרה לא lo קא משמע לן *mahu deteima
hani mili avodah dema'akvet kaparah aval avodah delo ma'akvet kaparah lo ka
mashma lan*. So we would have thought that the whole procedure
with washing hands and feet is only going to apply for things
that are מעכבת כפרה *ma'akvet kaparah*, works in the on the altar
like the זריקה *zrikah* or קבלה *kabalah* that we can't that we
need the washing hands and feet for, but a work that doesn't
necessitate it, that is not מעכבת כפרה *ma'akvet kaparah*, we don't. Therefore
the תורה *Torah* specifically says to us להקטיר אשה לה' *lehaktir isheh
laHashem*, קא משמע לן *ka mashma lan*, so that we know that.
One important piece for tonight,
for this morning, continue the conversation. We had a discussion yesterday,
I'm not sure where to put it in, okay. We had a
discussion yesterday, we have a split between רבי Rabbi *Rebbe* and רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar berabbi Shimon? *Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon*.
רבי Rebbe
*Rebbe* said that
water the hands and feet נפסל *nifsal*
in
the night overnight, נפסל בלינה *nifsal belinah*. And
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar berabbi Shimon *Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon*
said you can even go ten days ולא נפסל *velo nifsal*.
So that means they had this, do you remember that kind of
maybe?
We had a discussion in the middle of יט עמוד ב *Yud
Tet Amud Bet* and we're going to need it still today, we're
continuing that same discussion, that רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון
Rabbi Elazar berabbi
Shimon. *Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon* said the night doesn't matter. If you're
already in the מקדש Mikdash. *Mikdash* and you're serving, you don't have
to be מקדיש *makdish* your hands and feet again. And רבי Rebbe?
*Rebbe* said yes, the night פוסל *posel* and you have to be
מקדיש *makdish* again. And we're going to have a long discussion about
that. We're going to see רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* trying
to figure out, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* making a statement,
and then רבא Rava *Rava* and אביי Abaye *Abaye* trying to figure
out who's רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* going with and how
do we understand it going forward. Okay, so that's a little bit
of the overview of where we're going. כי אתא רב דימי אמר
רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan. בעא אילפא *ki ata Rav Dimi amar
Rabbi Yochanan ba'a Ilfa*. Okay, so who are who are all these
people? What are we doing? רב דימי *Rav Dimi* comes from ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael* to בבל Bavel *Bavel* and he teaches
about רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* that אילפא *Ilfa* had a
dilemma, raised an issue, which is going to in a roundabout way
going to be related to this. לדברי האומר אין ein לינה lina.
מועלת בקידוש ידים ורגלים yadayim v'raglayim. מי mi, כיור kiyor. מהו שיפסלו
*ledivrei ha'omer ein linah mo'elet be-kiddush yadayim ve-raglayim mei kiyor mahu she-yifsulu*?
Okay, so what is the situation? We now have the כיור kiyor
*kiyor*, the basin, with water,
and what happens to this water? If the water... stays overnight
in
the basin, is it פסול pasul *pasul* or is it usable?
Well, that's why they lower it down into a pool of water
so that it touches fresh water.
We'll get there.
No spoiler alert.
I actually found a mechanical כהן kohen. *kohen* in this דף *daf*,
so you know, this things, good things coming up.
But okay, so what is the situation? We have the כיור kiyor.
*kiyor*, right, the basin? And in the כיור kiyor *kiyor* there's water.
So
if
the water stays overnight, it might be פסול pasul בלינה *pasul belina*
like רבי Rabbi *Rebbi* says. But how can we say that it
doesn't? Because things that
are, stuff that was נעשה עבודה Avoda איתו *na'asa avoda ito*, things
that עבודה avoda. *avoda* in the מקדש Mikdash. *Mikdash* was done with
it would be פסול pasul *pasul*. So what about the water in
the כיור kiyor *kiyor*? Okay, we have our question kind of. Okay.
So
what are the two options? מי אמרינן *Mi amrinan*, הני למאי *hani
lemai*, what do we have the water in the כיור kiyor, *kiyor*
for? Okay, when we come to resolve it whether it's פסול pasul
*pasul* staying overnight or not, what do we have the water in
the כיור kiyor, *kiyor* for? לקידוש ידיים ורגליים *Lekidush yadayim veraglayim*. Okay,
obviously we know this, לקידוש ידיים ורגליים *lekidush yadayim veraglayim*. קידוש kiddush,
ידיים ורגליים גופיה *Kidush yadayim veraglayim gufeih* לא פסל בלינה *lo pasal
belina*. Okay, so once we prepared our hands, sanctified our hands,
themselves on the hands there's no more water and there's therefore no
פסול pasul. *psul*. In order for to have a פסול pasul, *psul*,
we have to have something that we can be פוסל *posel*. There's
no water on the hands and feet, no פסול pasul *psul*. או
*O*, alternatively, כיון דקדוש קדוש הוא בכלי שרת מפסלי *kevan dekadosh kadosh
hu bechli sharet mipsali*. Or does it go with the category that
anything that we've made some work with when morning has come and
night has gone by on it, then it's פסול pasul *pasul*. Okay,
we have another visitor coming from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael*
to בבל Bavel *Bavel*, and he's telling us something else. כי אתא
רבין *Ki ata Ravin* from ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* to בבל *Bavel*,
אמר amar רב ירמיה אמר רב אמי אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
*amar Rav Yirmiya amar Rav Ami amar Rabbi Yochanan*, הדר פשיט אילפא
*hadar pashit Ilfa*. He's like רבין
*Ravin* tells us in the name of רבי Rabbi, ירמיה *Rabbi Yirmiya*,
in the name of רב אמי *Rav Ami*, in the name of
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*, which is what we're concerned with,
אילפא *Ilfa* resolved this dilemma. After he asked the question, this dispute
resolved for him. כמחלוקת בזו כך מחלוקת בזו *Kemachloket bezo kach machloket
bezo*. Okay, so just like we have this dispute about the hands
and feet, רבי Rebbi. *Rebbi* says פסול pasul *pasul* and רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar berabbi Shimon. *Rabbi Elazar berabbi Shimon* says לא
פסול pasul. *lo pasul*, so we have about the כיור *kiyor*. So
we have about the sink with the water. What do you think
if you're still with me? No, no, no, what do you think?
This is the question. Who's going to say what about the כיור
*kiyor*?
Oh, so רבי Rebbi. *Rebbi* is going to say it's not valid,
and רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון,
Rabbi
Elazar berabbi Shimon right.
So רבי Rebbi *Rebbi* is going to say about the כיור *kiyor*
no, and רבי אלעזר בן שמעון Rabbi Elazar ben Shimon *Rabbi Elazar
ben Shimon* is going to say yes, even if it stays overnight,
it doesn't פסול *pasul*, it doesn't disqualify it. אמר לפניו רבי Rebbi
יצחק בר ביסנא *Amar lefanev Rabbi Yitzchak bar Bisna*: רבי Rebbi *Rebbi*,
אתה אומר כן *ata omer ken*? Like this is how you're planning
to solve our first thing by bringing us another problem that's not
quite resolved. אלא הכי אמר רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan.
שמעיה דאילפא *Ella hachi amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan shemeia de'Ilfa*:
כיור שלא שיקעו בערב *kiyor shelo shik'o ba'erev*, Michael, מקדש mikdash. ממנו
לעבודת לילה *mekadesh mimeno la'avodat layla*, ולמחר אינו מקדש eino mekadesh. *ulemachar
eino mekadesh*. Okay, so what is the situation? We have the sink,
as Michael was saying, and at night we lower it to the
spring, to
the מעיין *ma'ayan*, right? And by the water in the sink touching
the water of the מעיין *ma'ayan*, let's see you draw all that.
We don't have
to.
Okay.
By the water in the sink touching the water in the spring,
then it's going to be okay. Right? There's going to be like
a mix of new water and night water and somehow the water
is going to be okay. But here the thing is כיור שלא
שיקעו ממנו *kiyor shelo shik'u mimeno*. So we have a teaching that
a כיור שלא שיקעו בערב *kiyor shelo shik'u ba'erev*...
over that for some reason was not lowered to the מעיין, מקדש
ממנו לעבודת לילה ולמחר אינו מקדש. mekadesh mimenu l'avodat layla u'lemachar eino
mekadesh. Okay, so if we didn't lower the sink to the water,
we use it for the night and we use it for the
next morning, and
in the next morning it tells us אינו eino מקדש. mekadesh So
is that going to be proof enough in order to understand this
overnight procedure? והוין בה למחר אינו מקדש דלא צריך קידוש. ve-havin bah
lemachar eino mekadesh delo tsarikh kiddush. Okay, maybe the next day it
doesn't need קידוש, kiddush או דילמא איפסלו בלינה. o dilma ifsalu be-linah.
So the גמרא Gemara. rejects this, this is not like a good
enough proof, it's not a resolution because we don't know what is
the reason that למחר אינו מקדש. lemachar eino mekadesh. ולא פשט לן,
ve-la pasht lan, we didn't get an answer, ומר קפשט ליה מפשט,
u-mar ka-pasht lei mifshat, this is, we didn't get an answer and
you think that with this you're answering? All right, let's try to
answer it through another story. תא שמע, ta shema, here's our mechanical
כהן. kohen, בן קטין עשה שנים עשר דד לכיור. Ben Kattin asa
shenaim asar dad la-kiyor. So
Ben
Kattin was a כהן, kohen a high priest, and he fixed up
the כיור. Up until then the כיור had two spigots. I don't
know how to draw. This is the truth, I really don't know
how to draw.
Actually it's towards the bottom.
Okay, like this?
Yeah, because think about it,
if it's on the top it can't come out. Okay, great. All
right.
Those stories. Okay, so up until Ben Kattin there were two spigots
to the כיור. So now a כהן kohen would come,
somehow open the spigot, right, wash hands and feet, go into the
service. But sometimes there would be twelve כהנים, kohanim huh? Yeah, there'd
be a backup, like נטילת ידיים netilat yadayim in שול. shul. We're
just reliving the מקדש. mikdash So there'd be a backup and all
the כהנים kohanim would line up. Ben Kattin made the כיור so
it would have twelve spigots, so imagine this, six on this side
and six on the other side. And he also
did אף הוא עשה מוכני לכיור שלא יהיו מימיו נפסלים בלינה. af
hu asa mukhni la-kiyor shelo yehu meimav nifsalim be-linah. Okay, so he
created a pulley system, a גלגלת, galgelet, so that we can lower
the כיור to the spring and bring it up,
so that the water in the basin will not be פסול overnight
being in the מקדש. Mikdash. So we can learn from it. Now
think about how many years have gone by that they didn't do
it, right? 480 years of משכן Mishkan and days of בית ראשון
Bayit Rishon and all that, and now they're fixing it up.
Okay.
מאי לאו רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון? mai lav Rabbi Elazar berabbi Shimon?
So is it now
who is this according, according to who is this? Is it רבי
Rebbi that says it's פסול if it stays overnight or is it
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון? Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon
And the גמרא Gemara is asking: Oh, so it's probably
אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Elazar berabbi Shimon. He says: לא, רבי היא. lo,
Rabbi hi. This is שיטת רבי shitat Rabbi because we are afraid
that it's going to be פסול overnight. Therefore
we make sure we have a system to lower it down. Of
course we can understand also the opposite.
It's not. It's not. Don't worry. We're going to have a lot
of discussion that is not resolved, I'm sorry to be both the
spoiler and,
yeah, there's not going to be a satisfied thing at the
end
of the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. והא מדרישא רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון סיפא
נמי רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון.
ve-ha mid-reisha Rabbi Elazar berabbi
Shimon seifa nami Rabbi Elazar berabbi Shimon. We, we could have thought
from the beginning that it's רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi
Shimon. and infer from it that also the end is רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון. Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon And let's, let's elaborate. דקתני רישא,
de-katani reisha, going with the route that this might be according to
the system of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon גמרא
Gemara continues: בא לו אצל פרו ופר היה עומד בין האולם ולמזבח
ראשו לדרום ופניו למערב והכהן עומד במזרח ופניו למערב.
ba lo etsel paro u-far haya omed bein
ha-ulam ve-la-mizbe'ach rosho la-darom u-fanav la-ma'arav ve-ha-kohen omed ba-mizrach u-fanav la-ma'arav. Okay,
so let's, everybody has a picture? A drawing?
Yeah,
it's in the גמרא.
Gemara In case somebody's listening to us that doesn't have a map
in front of them. Okay, so we have שער ניקנור
Sha'ar Nicanor
ממזרח, mi'mizrach, מערב, ma'arav,
and
צפון, tzafon,
דרום. darom.
Okay,
מזבח mizbeach, and there's some discussion about where is the מזבח, mizbeach
is it here or middle, but let's say it's here. אולם ulam
and חליפות. chalifot. Yes?
It's close, right? There's some קשקושים kishkushim I would call them, yes?
You have like some designs on the thing, but roughly that's the
map.
Okay, so where is our פר? par?
Theoretically the פר par is, not theoretically, the פר par is standing
here with
its head to the דרום. darom. Okay, here he is. Don't worry.
It's not obvious, looks like a horse. Okay.
Okay,
with its head to the דרום. darom.
Theoretically I would have liked it to be
west-east.
But if I put it west-east, then when he does what he
does, not always knowing where he's going to do what he does,
it would be pointing east and that's considered לא כבוד. lo kavod.
So I'm going to put him like this and turn his face
to the מערב. ma'ariv. Okay, so this is what we just had.
פר היה עומד בין האולם ולמזבח ראשו לדרום פניו למערב.
par haya omed bein ha'ulam v'la'mizbeach rosho
la'darom u'fanav la'ma'ariv. Let's turn him this way.
והכהן עומד במזרח ופניו למערב. v'haKohen omed ba'mizrach u'fanav la'ma'ariv. Okay, מאן
שמעת ליה דאמר בין האולם
ולמזבח
צפון?
man shamta
lei d'amar bein ha'ulam v'la'mizbeach tzafon? Now, we know that קדשי קדשים
kodeshei kodashim have to be
brought
in the צפון. tzafon.
So in this map, where is the צפון? tzafon? The צפון tzafon
is here, right? The north is here. But is it here, here,
here? How far is this definition of צפון? tzafon? Right? Like when
people say I live in the north. I always used to say
I live in Northern California, but really California goes on another four
hundred miles after
this, just nobody thinks that there's a state there. So the same
kind of conversation is going on here. דתניא, d'tanya, איזהו צפון? eizehu
tzafon? Where is the צפון? tzafon? מקיר
מזבח צפוני ועד כותל עזרה צפוני וכנגד כל המזבח כולו צפון. mi'kir
mizbeach tzfoni v'ad kotel azara tzfoni u'keneged kol hamizbeach kulo tzafon. דברי
רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yossi bar Rabbi Yehuda. So
this would be מקיר מזבח צפוני, mi'kir mizbeach tzfoni, so this would
be here, right? From the צפון tzafon of the מזבח mizbe'ach, all
the way. רבי אלעזר בר רבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Shimon
מוסיף, mosif, אף בין האולם ולמזבח. af bein ha'ulam v'la'mizbeach. Okay, so
this area too between the אולם. ulam.
I should have different colors and all the good things. Okay, רבי
Rebbi מוסיף, mosif, אף מקום דריסת רגלי הכהנים ומקום דריסת רגלי ישראל.
af mekom drisat raglei hakohanim u'mekom drisat raglei Yisrael. So also here
where they're walking.
אבל מן החליפות ולפנים הכל מודים שפסול. aval min hachalifot u'lifnim hakol
modim she'pasul. So the חליפות chalifot is the area where they left
their knives and so that area is פסול for, isn't
it Yiddish a חלף chalaf for a knife?
I don't know that.
What? How do you say? חלף. chalaf.
חליפות chalifot חלף. chalaf. A knife? I thought...
no I don't know and in Hebrew it's like סכין. sakin. סכין
sakin and חליפה chalifa is a suit, so I don't know. Okay.
Okay, ותסברה v'tispra
רבי אלעזר בר רבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Shimon ולא רבי?
v'lo Rebbe? Like how did you prove from this that this is
רבי אלעזר בר רבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Shimon and not
רבי? Rebbi אדי רבי יוסי בר רבי יהודה מוסיף אדי רבי אלעזר
בר רבי שמעון לא מוסיף. adei Rabbi Yossi bar Rabbi Yehuda mosif
adei Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Shimon lo mosif. So the area that
seemed north according to רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar בן שמעון Shimon, is
included in the area that רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi
assigns as north. Different colors would have helped. So therefore the first
clause of the משנה Mishnah can also be in accordance with the
opinion of רבי יהודה הנשיא. Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi. Like we didn't help
anything with this. So let's try a different proof.
אנן הכי קאמרינן. Anan hachi kamrinan. אי סלקא דעתך isalka da'atakh רבי
Rebbi היא, hi, if you think it's רבי, Rebbi לוקמה lokma במקום
דריסת רגלי כהנים bimkom drisat raglei kohanim ובמקום דריסת רגלי ישראל. uvimkom
drisat raglei yisrael. If
you
think that this is according to רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi,
so then we can put the bull somewhere else. Because we put
him here, but we really can put him down here. We can
just bring him in through the gate and put him right here
because according to רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi, this also would
be צפון. tzafon.
Okay, so we can just slaughter it here. אלא מאי, Ela mai,
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon היא? hi? How do
we, why do we think it's opposite? לוקמה מקיר מזבח צפוני עד
כותל עזרה צפוני.
Lokma mikir mizbe'ach tzefoni ad kotel
azara tzefoni. Between here and the עזרה. azara.
Okay. אלא מאי, Ela mai, אלא מאי אית לך למימר, ela mai
itlekh lemeimar, משום חולשא דכהן גדול. mishum chulsha dekhohen gadol. Why are
we, why are we okay, so let the bull stand
between this wall and the מזבח, Mizbeiach, and why are we not
doing this?
Why is it positioned between the here in the אולם? ulam? משום
חולשא דכהן גדול. mishum chulsha dekhohen gadol. We could have slaughtered this
poor bull closer to the gate maybe, but the כהן גדול kohen
gadol is doing his עבודה avodah here. And this is on יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. And כהן גדול, kohen gadol, poor guy, it's hard
for him this day. He's fasting, he's running back and forth, he's
up all night doing the קרבנות, korbanot, so we're trying to make
it easier for him. Not because this is a proof to us
on where is the צפון, tzafon, but because we feel for the
כהן גדול. kohen gadol. So therefore, we don't slaughter okay, הכא נמי
משום חולשא דכהן גדול. hacha nami mishum chulsha dekhohen gadol. We don't
slaughter the פר, par, the פר, par, the פר par in the
entrance even though we could because it's צפון tzafon here too, but
slaughter it here because it helps the כהן kohen and it doesn't
solve for us the problem of the כיור, but we are done
with this topic for now. Alright, we haven't solved it.
We'll come back to it later, but from a different side. Okay.
אמר רבי
יוחנן.
Rabbi Yochanan I
think we had that discussion in a different way just not so
long ago about that he could do it right up to the
אולם. ulam.
I don't remember, but it looks so cool.
You remember? What? That he could bring the sacrifice, rather bring the
blood. We were discussing the blood before, right? Yeah, that's where the
right. בכל חטאת
או חטאת השמנה. Bechol chatat, o chatat hashomem. Yeah.
But this is specifically the פר par on יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. But the הלכה, halacha, that's where we had
it I think.
Oh right, right, right.
That's what it was
right.
But the same discussion about what was considered north or not in
that
sense, similar in terms of הלכה. halacha. Yeah.
Alright, coming up to my favorite עבודה avoda, in the מקדש.
mekadesh?
תרומת הדשן. Terumat hadeshen. אמר רבי יוחנן קידש ידיו ורגליו לתרומת הדשן
למחר אינו צריך לקדש שכבר קידש מתחילת עבודה. Amar Rabbi Yochanan, kidesh
yadav veraglav leterumat hadeshen, lemachar eino tzarich lekadesh shekevar kidesh mitechilat avoda.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that the כהן kohen should קידש ידיו?
kidesh yadav? Do you want to say? No, no, it's okay, you
go ahead. The כהן kohen is going to be מקדש mekadesh his
hands and feet for תרומת הדשן. terumat hadeshen. תרומת הדשן Terumat hadeshen
is the removal of the ashes from the sacrifices that have been
burned all night long. Basically, and this is the opening of פרשת
צו, Parashat Tzav, this is the first כהן kohen in the morning,
if I understand correctly, first כהן kohen. in the morning coming and
taking out the garbage before starting the new day. And I think
on so many levels, so many levels it's amazing. Maybe they could
have had somebody else take out the garbage. Maybe the כהנים Kohanim
could have said, no, that's not a job I'm going to do,
I am a כהן. kohen, So already that that is like a
very humiliating task. Yes, you're a כהן, Kohen you're doing important things,
you're sacrificing things on behalf of all the people, and guess what?
You get to go down to take down the garbage and that's
also a respectful job. And another thing is that symbolically that too
symbolically it's like
for us for the מקדש Mikdash whatever it is we have to
empty things out before we put new things in. We have to
clear our mind when we come to learn new things. Whatever, it's
just
symbolically spiritually I find it very nice. Okay. So all night long
there was עבודה avoda. in the מקדש. Mikdash First thing כהן Kohen
comes and takes out the garbage and then
according to
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan למחר lemachar אינו eino צריך tzarich לקדש lekadesh
שכבר shekvar קידש kidesh מתחלת mitchalat העבודה. ha-avoda. So he already prepared
himself, right, for the service
and
you could say something instead of the word garbage. You could you
know see it as something still sanctified, right?
Yes, it is, it is. But do we think that in our
own life when we have to take stuff out?
No, but that's the difference what I'm saying is this was
elevated. In our own life we're taking out the garbage.
It's a long think about it, that's a long whatever, spiritual kind
of discussion, right? If everything is blah blah blah then...
right right right. I was thinking of defining what we're talking about
garbage. I was thinking about like you know the food after the
dinner or something like that. As you might be thinking about something
spiritual.
One person's garbage, another person's leftover. Yes.
True, right?
No,
but how do we look at things in our life? Are we
like 'eh' or are we like
oh that's compost, right?
Or that's clothing for somebody else? I should fold them nicely, I
shouldn't just throw them in the... right
right right. Like I think to me there's like a whole thing
around this so we don't have to sit there, but just something
to think about
on
a greater meaning of like just doing this. Okay. למן. le-man. Okay.
לפי lefi מי, according to who is רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan saying
that he does not have to go, right? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
is telling us למחר lemachar אינו eino צריך tzarich לקדש lekadesh שכבר
shekvar
קידש kidesh מתחלת mitchalat העבודה. ha-avoda.
According to who is רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan saying this that the
כהן kohen now does not need to go back and be מקדש?
Mikdash, אי i לרבי le-Rabbi אלעזר Elazar ברבי berabi שמעון, Shimon, if
it's according to רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon הא
ha אמר אין צריך tzarich לקדש lekadesh אפילו afilu מכאן mikan ועד
ve-ad עשרה asara ימים. yamim. Okay, if it's according to... wait a
second where is my... okay,
if it's according to רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon
he said that you don't have to be מקדש Mikdash, even if
you work ten days, consecutive ten days. So...
so like kind of of course that's not a problem.
But רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said
למחר. lemachar. למחר lemachar אינו eino צריך tzarich לקדש lekadesh and we're
going to see that this is going to be some sort of
discussion.
Okay. Did the כהנים kohanim work a 24-hour shift for 10 days
or through the night?
Well, if he's coming first thing in the morning to do תרומת
הדשן Trumat HaDeshen and he's...
so there is, you'll see in a minute here...
when is he coming? When is first thing in the morning or
is he coming at the end of the night before dawn has
risen to clear the previous day to prepare for the next day?
Because here...
okay here is
אביי Abaye who thinks about רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan
Okay אביי Abaye is here and רבא Rava is going to be
here. We got this right.
אביי Abaye thinks this is according to רבי. Rebbi, The fact that
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says קידש kidesh
ידיו yadav ורגליו ve-raglav לתרומת le-Trumat
הדשן HaDeshen למחר lemachar אינו
צריך tzarich לקדש lekadesh שכבר shekvar קידש kidesh מתחלת mitchalat העבודה. ha-avoda.
This statement of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan? according to אביי Abaye is
according to רבי. Rabbi, ולינה ve-lina
דרבנן de-rabanan היא. hi. ומודי u-modei רבי Rabbi.
דמקראת de-mikrat הגבר ha-gever ועד ve-ad צפרא tzafra לא פסלה לינה. pasla
linah
Okay
so we have this period in the day that is before pre-dawn
from מקראת הגבר. mikrat ha-gever. What is a גבר? gever? We... a
masculine caller?
Yes.
So we... it could either be a trained rooster that knows when
to call us right early in the morning or maybe it's a
person that that's their job, that's their task to call early in
the morning and let people know that dawn is coming.
So there... רבי Rabbi, is מודה modeh there for that little time
between קריאת הגבר kriyat ha-gever and until the morning that it doesn't
פסלה pasla לינה lina that so somebody who prepares his hands and
feet at that time... time he can continue to perform the tasks
of the מקדש Mikdash, going forward, okay? רבא Rava says
לעולם le'olam רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar be'rabbi Shimon, הכי ראה
דבריו he ra'ah devarav בתחילת עבודה ולא בסוף עבודה. bit-chilat avodah v'lo
besof avodah. רבא Rava says no this
statement of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that is in accordance with
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabbi Elazar berabbi shimon,
Why and he saw this he saw sorry he saw this that
this is correct in regards to the beginning of the service that
somebody a priest a כהן kohen may serve during the day
on the like קידוש kiddush on the on the קידוש Kiddush that
he did just before dawn but he does not agree with him
with regards to the end of the service which is
a whole discussion I'm probably not going to have right now how
can רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who is an אמורא Amora right he's
a later
rabbi
250 300 to common era how can he be in dispute with
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar berabbi shimon about part of the
service?
Okay maybe.
מיתיבי. Meitivei. All right let's try to learn let's try to continue
and resolve it or
what was that chronology by the way can you just that you
just רבי Rabbi, is around 200 right רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehudah
HaNasi is the one writing the משנה Mishnah
compiling right so he's around 200 to common era רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan is around 250 300
and אביי Abaye and רבא Rava 3
somewhere there also important piece is that these are in Israel רבי
Rabbi. יוחנן was in טבריה. Tveria.
רבי יוחנן and רבי are in Israel.
Yeah רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar ben Rabbi Shimon. I believe
too so like this early discussion is in Israel and that's why
in the beginning of this morning's learning we had these rabbis that
come from בבל from ארץ ישראל sorry from ארץ ישראל to בבל
and are like listen listen this is what רבי יוחנן taught no
no listen listen this is what רבי יוחנן taught and he meant
to follow רבי no no he meant to follow רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון Rabbi Elazar berabbi shimon and again under this assumption that anytime
now the temple is going to be I like when I learn
it there's a part of me that can sense their panic it's
like anytime now the temple is going to be somehow rebuilt
and
we're not ready like we can't figure out how to do this
we have disagreements about you know the קדושה kedushah and when the
כהנים Kohanim should do what we have to figure this out.
So what were you questioning about who could be discussing with whom
because of the chronology you said something about רבי יוחנן?
רבי יוחנן criticized or like accepts part of what רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar ברבי berabi שמעון Shimon, says he says sorry
where was it yeah the רישא reisha and the סיפא seifa yes
yes yes.
Right so what were you saying about how the chronology didn't work?
Usually
the אמוראים Amoraim accept what
the תנאים Tannaim are saying right like we accept what previous generations
are saying and then try to work with it oh he didn't
mean it this way he didn't mean it that way but רבי
יוחנן says רבא Rava says that רבי יוחנן agrees with רבי אלעזר
ברבי berabi שמעון on the בתחילת העבודה ולא בסוף העבודה bit-chilat ha'avodah
v'lo besof ha'avodah not in regards to how the end of the
service should be. And where's רבא Rava? where what year is רבא?
Rava Somewhere here 3 to 400 he's there also okay they're like
contemporaries right they always come together אביי Abaye and רבא Rava yes.
What does that translate into what
this כהן Kohen is doing? What in this
service
specifically? Yeah when is he when does
he start a shift
and when is he leaving? Oh my understanding is he
comes when the like right
at the when the גבר gever is calling whoever the גבר gever
is the that's the אביי Abaye version right? No this says it
says on it ומודי דמקריאת הגבר ועד צפרא לא פסלה לינה umodeh
d'mikriat hagever v'ad tzipra lo paslah linah like רבי agrees everybody. Wait,
the alarm goes off tell him I'm ready to go from the
sun that everybody agrees that if the כהן Kohen works there, it
doesn't constitute the previous day. Like and see, see the next thing.
Okay. And so רבא's Rava, comment is also talking about that gap
and is just saying it is the previous day. Let me
see. Yeah, yeah, yeah, that the כהן Kohen can serve in the
מקדש Mikdash. kind of
as far as his on the strength of the קידוש kiddush that
he did just before dawn, right? That he prepared for the day.
But he didn't agree with him in regards to the end of
the service. How long does this last? Is it going? He said
he can be there for 10 days.
Right? Once he started and he's inside, he can just continue working
because this is the discussion we had
yesterday, בבואם
ובגישתם. bevo'am
u'vigishtam.
גמרא Gemara rollercoaster. We had two
options. Yes. Okay.
רבי said בגישתם. begishtam. In the פסוק which we just read to
start this morning off, we had two words. Well, we had a
lot of words in that פסוק. But there were two descriptions on
how the כהנים Kohanim, come to do the holy work. They can
be ניגש, nigash, approaching, or they can be בא, ba, they're coming.
Okay, so let's say a כהן Kohen is coming in the whatever,
whenever, whatever hour is his shift, right? He's coming to the מקדש,
mekadesh he's washing his hands, he's inside the מקדש, mekadesh and he's
just running his errands, whatever it is. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, if
I understand him correctly, for 10 days he can be inside, he
already did his קידושא kiddusha of hands and feet walking in, he's
fine.
רבי says no, not בבואם, not when they enter, but when they
approach the עבודה. avoda. So if I'm inside the מקדש, Mikdash right,
but I am right now whatever, resting in the shade and now
I'm going to be ניגש, nigash, I'm going to approach to do
a sacrifice, I should wash again. And that's the difference between them.
And this is why for רבי, the overnight means you have to
restart the עבודת קודש avodat kodesh and for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
means you're fine.
More or less.
מיתיבי. metivei. Okay. גמרא Gemara brings us a משנה Mishnah from מסכת
תמיד. Masechet Tamid. ראוהו אחיו הכהנים שירד והן רצו ובאו
מהרו וקידשו ידיהם ורגליהם מן הכיור.
ra'uhu echav hakohanim sheyarad v'hen ratzu
u'vau miharu v'kidshtu yedeihem v'ragleihem min hakiyor. Beautiful
image. The brethren or real brothers, כהנים, Kohanim see the כהן Kohen
that's taking out the דשן, deshen, I'll use instead of the garbage,
the leftover of yesterday's
or overnight burnings.
They see him that he does
that, it's like a sign, right, that the day has begun. Yesterday
has been cleared. We can now come in and this. הם רצו,
hem ratzu, right, they run and come and they
do the קידוש kiddush. of hands and feet. Where are they? In
the כיור, right? They come to the basin to
wash their hands and feet. So now what do we learn from
it?
So this is going to be the question in front of us.
Overnight before didn't, was not valid.
Okay, so wait.
You and I reading this made an assumption which the גמרא Gemara
is going to work with, but think about it, we made an
assumption. You'll see. Just hold the suspense. Just now
a second, a half a second pause to think about this whole
miraculous situation. You know when I was listening, preparing it, the Rabbi
I was listening to he's saying think about us burning חמץ, chametz,
right? You just have like a little pile and three seconds later
if the flame is too high, right, then you're like, I can't
stand here, I gotta go away somewhere. And here the כהנים Kohanim
are all night long burning things on the מזבח, whatever meat left
over animals were brought to them, take it care of it and
their tunics and the whole and the whole thing it's like a
miraculous existence that takes place in the מקדש. Mikdash Okay. All
right. So now we're trying to understand what is this situation with
the כהנים Kohanim. that were told in the משנה Mishna in מסכת
תמיד: Masechet Tamid: רצו ובאו מהרו וקידשו ידיהם ורגליהם מן הכיור. ratzu
uba'u miharu vekideshu yedeihem veragleihem min hakiyor. Right?
They see the first כהן kohen of the morning, they're running and
they're doing this קידוש. kiddush This two options: בשלמא לאביי דמוקים לה
כרבי. bishlama le'Abaye damokim lah kerabbi.
If
this is according to אביי which agrees with
רבי, ומודה רבי u'modeh Rabbi דמקרוה הגבר עד צפרא לא פסלה לינה.
de-mikrot hagever ad tzafra lo pasla linah.
So even though this was like the end of the night, the
לינה linah doesn't make it פסול. הא מני? Ha'mani? רבי. So we'll
assume this is רבי, right? They're starting the day and they are
washing
their hands. אלא לרבא דמוקים לה כרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Ella le-Rava
damokim lah kerabbi elazar berabbi shimon. Okay.
So if we can think that there maybe they were not inside
and now they're coming. אבל לרבי מקרוה הגבר ועד צפרא פסלה לינה.
Aval le-Rabbi mikrot hagever ve'ad tzafra pasla linah. הא מני? Ha'mani? Okay,
so let me write this. According to רבא, who accepts the teaching
in accordance with רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, who holds it according to
this okay. So and everybody holds at this period that we mentioned
from מקרוה הגבר mikrot hagever until the morning is פסלה pasla לינה
then then in accordance to whose opinion is this משנה. Mishna. If
it's רבי, then we understand, right, the overnight makes it פסול,
things that were left overnight make it פסול and we have to
be מקדש Mikdash, from the beginning. אי רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון? Ei
Rabbi Elazar berabbi shimon? האמר אפילו מכאן ועד עשרה ימים אינו צריך
לקדש. Ha'amar afilu mikan ve'ad asara yamim eino tzarich lekadesh. But if
it's this is exactly what we mentioned. If it's according to רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון who said that even for ten days you don't
have to be מקדש mekaddesh, so what is the situation? Why are
they going to wash? Right? We made a we made an assumption
David that the גמרא Gemara is going to take away. לעולם כרבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Le-olam kerabbi Elazar ben Rabbi Shimon. Whoops. This is
like according to רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Why? והכא במאי עסקינן? Ve-hacha
bemai askinan? What is the exact situation that we're dealing with here?
בכהני חדתי. Be-Kohanei chadati. We're talking about new כהנים. Kohanim We assumed
that these are כהנים Kohanim that are in the מקדש mikadesh right
and therefore we get a proof to רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda
haNasi right to רבי. We assumed that it was כהנים Kohanim. that
were already in the מקדש mikadesh and here they're approaching a new
task and they're washing therefore they're strengthening this opinion. But no בכהני
חדתי Be-Kohanei chadati so these are כהנים חדשים, Kohanim chadashim, new כהנים.
kohanim This is the first time they come to the מקדש, mikadesh
they did not wash yesterday hands and feet and so now they
they need to do so. That doesn't really does it? I'm asking
you. Does it really does it explain the whole dispute? I mean
that just like is an easy way to say you know a
new it's not what we're talking about. We're not talking about the
same thing. Yeah. We're just talking about this particular one, right? Like
we're trying to bring the משנה Mishna to help us and then
we're saying doesn't quite help us because these are כהנים חדשים Kohanim
chadashim and both agree that כהנים חדשים Kohanim chadashim need to and
this is רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון says בבואם when they come they
wash. So are they strengthening this or are they strengthening this? Right.
So there's no there's no decision right right about which they understand
not at least not yet. If if. Okay. Moving on. That's a
very typical גמרא Gemara move is you bring a proof and you
say well it doesn't... It might support this, but if you read
it this way it might support that, so it's not really a
proof of either side. Okay, on to the next one. We keep
pulling out potential proofs and kind of saying they don't really get
you there. Yes, they get you partially there, but they don't quite
get you there. Until sometimes you leave it at we don't know
and sometimes you leave it with a resolution. Right. And sometimes you're
just like, okay, I don't know what to do with this, moving
on. Right? Yeah, kind of thing. Okay. Wow, a little tiny long
bit of text. Okay. איבעיא להו יציאה מהו שתועיל בקידוש ידים ורגלים.
Ibayya lehu yetzia mahu she-to'il be-kiddush yadayim ve-raglayim. Okay, so we have
a couple of problems. And we need to spell out the next,
the previous problem which we didn't spell out in order to deal
with the next problem. Challenge, no problems, right? Okay. From דאורייתא, De-Oraita,
there is no concept of טומאת ידים. tumat yadayim. Okay, a person
can be either טמא tamei or טהור. tahor. We don't know anything
from the
Torah that a person can be half טמא tamei and half טהור.
tahor. This part טמא, tamei, this part טהור. tahor. Like we don't,
we don't have that. This is a תקנה takanah from
the Rabbis that כהנים when they touch certain things like the קרבן
korban that is פיגול piggul or נותר, notar, like קרבנות korbanot that
were not done appropriately, that they will be מטמא metamei ידים yadayim
and therefore we've been talking about this whole thing of קידוש ידים
ורגלים. kiddush yadayim ve-raglayim. And now we're going to try to see
what happens with a כהן kohen who is going out outside the
עזרה azarah
related to this discussion
and following these two opinions. And guess what are some of the
things that will come up?
When I say going out, right, leaving, what do I mean? Here
I can do it on the screen really good. Is it like
this? Am I still on the screen? Is it like that? What...
Okay, alright. איבעיא להו יציאה מהו שתועיל בקידוש ידים ורגלים.
Ibayya lehu yetzia mahu she-to'il be-kiddush
yadayim ve-raglayim. What is... what are we doing with somebody that's going
out? How much going outing is פסול and needs to resanctify, and
how much is still okay? אם תמצי לומר לינה לא פסלה דלא
פריש אבל יציאה דפרש יש אסוחי מסח דעתיה Im timtzi lomar lina
lo pasla de-lo parish aval yetzia de-parash yesh asuchei masach da'ateih או
דלמא כיון דבידו לחזור לא מסח. O dilma keivan de-veyado lachzor lo
masach. So like, does it in effect make a פסול our sanctification,
right, and need to be re-entered? If you say that things that
are being left overnight are not disqualified, i.e., not disqualified means they
remain fit, then maybe it's only because they, like, it didn't separate
themselves from the temple, but leaving the temple where the, like the
כהן kohen actually separates himself, right, he is פורש poresh from the
temple, he's going away, is it possible that this is part of
the עבודה avoda or is it... or is the כהן kohen becoming
distracted? He has הסחת הדעת, hasachat ha-da'at, אסוחי מסח דעתיה. asuchei masach
da'ateih. Or because he's like, oh, I'm just going to get whatever,
I'm just going to get a spoon so that I can, right,
do the עבודת קודש, avodat kodesh, then his mind is still on
this. He just physically happened to be outside, but he's not
מסיח דעתו, mesiach da'ato,
כיון דבידו לחזור לא מסיח. keivan de-veyado lachzor lo mesiach. Okay. So
we're going to have four תשמע'ס, ta shema's, hopefully. We'll go through
that quickly,
maybe. Four תשמע'ס ta shema's that will not help us solve it.
So I apologize in advance. Okay, so now we can
read them fast
because they... we know they're not going to help us. תשמע Ta
shema number one, if you want to mark it or asterisk, then
it will help organize the text. תשמע. Ta shema. קידש ידיו ורגליו
ונטמאו מטבילן ואין צריך לקדש יצאו הרי הן בקדושתן.
Kiddesh yadav ve-raglav ve-nitme'u
matbilan ve-ein tzarich lekadesh yatze'u harei hen bi-kdushatan. Okay. So somebody, right,
the translation is like מקדש נפסל, mekuddash nifsal, so I'm translating from
Hebrew to Hebrew. But okay, so if he's מקדש, mekadesh he's preparing
his hands and feet, something happened, they touched a טומאה, tumah, he...
dips them again, מטביל matbil again, and he doesn't need to do
the sanctify again. And if, if they leave, who's they? Because you're
reading how I went to... okay fine.
So again, if he, he, pronouns, English pronouns, if he מקדש Mikdash.
his hands and feet, blah blah blah, and they left, who's they?
His hands and feet, if they left, then they still are, remained
in their קדושה. kdusha. So this is the picture I showed earlier,
if just the hands leave, then they still remain in קדושה. kdusha.
So that could be a proof that going out is not, yeah,
שיציאה she-yetzia is
not לא פוסלת. lo poselet. יצאו
ידיו לא קמיבעי לן כי קמיבעי לן יצא כל גופו. Yatza'u yadav
la ka miba'i lan, ki ka miba'i lan yatza kol gufo. Okay,
it's like the גמרא Gemara is a little bit saying, what, are
you playing with me? I wasn't asking about just putting the hands
out the window, right, through in the car when you're driving, I
just put the hands out the window, is that really meaning I
am outside? I'm talking about the whole body. Not good. תא שמע
Ta shma second one. שלא רחץ ידיו ורגליו מקדש בכלי שרת מבפנים.
Shelo rachatz yadav v'raglav mikadesh b'kli sharet mibifnim. קדש בכלי שרת בחוץ
או בכלי חול מבפנים או שטבל במי מערה ועבד עבודתו פסולה. Kiddesh
b'kli sharet bachutz o b'kli chol mibifnim o she-taval b'mei me'arah v'avad
avodato psulah. So if he didn't, he doesn't wash his... wait wait
wait, okay, hands and feet blah blah blah. Yes, okay, so if
he washes his hands, which he does this רחיצת ידים ורגלים, rechizat
yadayim v'raglayim, it must be with a vessel that is inside the
temple. If he does it with a כלי kli that's outside or
with a כלי kli that has sand or with the, whatever, in
the cave water or something like that, then it's פסול. Basically, if
he מקדש mekadesh his hands incorrectly, he's מחלל, mechalel, he's פוסל את
העבודה. posel et ha-avoda. גמרא Gemara gives this commentary. טעמא דקדש בכלי
שרת בחוץ הא קדש בפנים ויצא עבודתו כשרה. Ta'ama d'kiddesh b'kli sharet
bachutz, ha kiddesh bifnim v'yatza avodato ksherah. So why you bringing me
example from somebody who's being מקדש mekadesh outside? That was not my
question. My question was about somebody who's inside and going out. So
if you're bringing me this example, I would understand that he's if
he's קדש בפנים ויצא עבודתו כשרה. kiddesh bifnim v'yatza avodato ksherah. And
the גמרא Gemara responds or tries to deal with it. דילמא קדש
בכלי שרת בחוץ היכי דמי. Dilma kiddesh b'kli sharet bachutz heichi dami.
What, what are we talking about that he's, what is the situation?
What is the מציאות metziut of somebody who's מקדש בכלי שרת בחוץ?
mikadesh b'kli sharet bachutz? כגון דאפיק ידיו לבר וקדש הא קדש בפנים
ויצא דאפיק ידיה לבר כשרה אבל יצא כל גופו תיבעי לך. K'gon
d'afik yadav l'var v'kiddesh, ha kiddesh bifnim v'yatza d'afik yadeih l'var ksherah
aval yatza kol gufo tiba'i lach. So you're giving me an example
of somebody maybe having his body inside and he's doing the קידוש
kidush outside, and I need to know about his whole body. You
should like, you should raise something that has to do with his
whole body and that question is still not resolved. תא שמע Ta
shma number three. אמר ליה רב זביד לרב פפא תא שמע יצא
חוץ למחיצת חומת העזרה אם לשהות טעון טבילה אם לפי שעה טעון
קידוש ידים ורגלים.
Amar lei Rav Zvid l'Rav Pappa, ta shma, yatza chutz l'mechizat
chomat ha-azarah, im lishhot ta'un tvilah, im l'fi sha'ah ta'un kiddush yadayim
v'raglayim. Okay, so I'm going to bring another ברייתא. braita. In the
case where the כהן kohen leaves the חומת העזרה, chomat ha-azarah, if
he does so לשהות, lishhot, if he's like he's going in order
to stay outside, שהייה, shehiya, right, we have it in שבת. Shabbat.
If he does this for a long time, then he requires טבילה,
tvila, he requires immersion. But what if לפי שעה? l'fi sha'ah? What
if just like for a short time, for a moment? Then he
needs the, this is what we're talking about, he needs the sanctification
of ידים ורגלים. So this is from this ברייתא. braita. And רב
פפא Rav Pappa is going to be דוחה. doche. אמר ליה הכא
במאי עסקינן. Amar lei hacha b'mai askinan. What is this ברייתא braita
that you're bringing me here as a proof? It's not good, why?
כגון שיצא להסך רגליו ולהטיל מים. K'gon she-yatza l'hasech raglav u-l'hatil mayim.
This here we're dealing with somebody who went to the bathroom. להסך
רגליו ולהטיל מים, L'hasech raglav u-l'hatil mayim, this is number two and
number one. So if the כהן Kohen for whatever reason, we talked
about it earlier, was not Ready already in the morning for the
עבודה, we talked about diets and all sorts of things, and now
he needs to go to the bathroom, then of course he needs
to be מקדש ידיים ורגליים mekadesh yadayim veraglayim when he comes back
in, and the גמרא challenges this: הבהדיא קתני לה, כל המסיח רגליו
טעון טבילה.
Habahadya katni lah, kol hamesiach raglav
taun tvila. We already have another משנה, Mishna, this one is in
יומא Yoma that teaches that anyone that goes to the bathroom, right,
he needs to be מקדש ידיים ורגליים. mekadesh yadayim veraglayim. וכל המטיל
מים טעון קידוש ידיים ורגליים.
vechol hamatil mayim taun
kidush yadayim veraglayim. תני והדר מפרש, Tani vehadar mefarash, like this is
a principle that has been taught and now we're explaining and repeating
again, but it doesn't help us with our question because our question
was not about going to the bathroom. תא שמע Ta shema number
four. By the way, I thought that that's just an answer, well
we're saying it again, doesn't it mean if we said it once
and repeated it, we need to learn something new from the ברייתא?
Baraita? I don't know, can't do anything with it. This is what
I have. תני והדר מפרש, Tani vehadar mefarash, yes. It's saying that
every time a כהן Kohen moves his bowels, he has to immerse
himself in a מקוה. Mikvah. He has to טעון טבילה taun tvila
move his bowels, yes, number two. Every time. If he just goes
number one, he has to be מקדש ידיים ורגליים. mekadesh yadayim veraglayim.
Or only if he's in... remember we had a discussion that he's
supposed to go in the morning, and if he doesn't go in
the morning it's like he interferes with his service, with the flow
of the day, and then we had discussions about that
he goes and then he goes in a מקוה Mikvah before he
starts his עבודה. Right, right, before he puts his clothes and then
he's מקדש mekadesh and then he walks in.
We'll do
תא שמע ta shema number four and then pause I think. Okay.
תא שמע פרה, Ta shema Para, okay,
maybe we can learn from the service of the פרה אדומה Para
Aduma of the red heifer.
רבי חייא בר יוסף אמר: מקדש בכלי שרת בפנים ויוצא. ורבי יוחנן
אמר: אפילו בחוץ ואפילו בכלי חול ואפילו במקידה של חרס.
Rabbi Chiyya bar Yosef amar: mekadesh bichli sharet bifnim veyotze. Verabbi Yochanan
amar:
afilu bachutz veafilu bichli chol veafilu bimkida shel cheres.
With regards to
the service of the פרה אדומה, Para Aduma, this takes place outside
the temple, right, outside the מקדש. רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya says in
the preparation he prepares his hands and feet in
the כלי שרת, kli sharet, right, in the
service vessel inside the temple, and then he leaves the
temple.
What do you think, is this going
to be a good proof? Not necessarily because it's not an עבודה.
העבודה Ha'avoda itself is outside, right, so it's not going to quite
help us. Okay, ורבי יוחנן Verabbi Yochanan said he can sanctify... like
he can be מקדש his hands even outside the temple and even
with a כלי חול, kli chol, right, not a כלי שרת. kli
sharet. I said something wrong earlier. Even like with a non-מקדש vessel
and even with a מקידה mkida which is made out of חרס,
cheres, out of earthenware, which would be not כשר. kasher. So this
leaving of the temple does not disqualify, right, the קידוש of hand
and feet because the עבודה itself is outside. And this is what
רב פפא Rav Pappa is going to say. אמר רב פפא: שאני
פרה, הואיל וכל מעשיה בחוץ, לא פסלה ביציאה. אי הכי, למה לי
דמקדש? כעין עבודה פנים. Amar Rav Pappa: shani Para, ho'il vechol ma'aseha
bachutz, lo pasla biyetziah. Iy hachi, lama li demikdash? Ke'eyn avoda pnim.
רב פפא Rav Pappa says the whole heifer is done outside and
not in the עזרה, Azara, so why do I need the כהן
to be מקדש his hands and feet at all for this service
of the פרה אדומה? Para Aduma? And the גמרא says it's like
it's done as much as possible like things that are being done
inside the temple, but it's still, we still have no answer. I
think we'll pause for today and continue with the suspenseful עבודת מקדש
avodat mikdash tomorrow. Thank you for being with us. Thank you.